all right the next video is going to be
28 minutes long it's from ma alasen
sustainability under active
inference hey everyone my name is
maras PhD candidate at the University
Quebec and director of research strategy
at
versus today I'm going to be talking to
you about budding work on sustainability
under active inference which we had
started with multiple authors that I
listed down below uh starting from the
core components and scaling up to a
computational model we are pursuing this
research in multiple collaborations ADV
verses around sustainability ultimately
this is meant to Charter a path to much
larger projects so feel free to reach
out if if you want to
collaborate so let's begin with the most
fundamental aspect of sustainability
namely
resilience resilience refers to an agent
or system's ability to persist and adapt
in the face of challenges or
perturbations under active inference
resilience is a multifaceted concept
involving different strategies that
allow a system to maintain or recover
functional stability
resilience can be broken down into three
core components inertia elasticity and
plasticity so let's start by defining
inertia it describes an agent's capacity
to resist change when subjected to
external
disturbances it really is the stability
and robustness of a
system in active inference inertia is
represented by high Precision beliefs
which can be thought of as highly
confident low entropy beliefs about the
system's current
state inertia is reflected in the
Precision weighing of prediction errors
higher Precision implies stronger
resistance to updating beliefs
maintaining a stable State uh means that
Precision is implemented as a scaling
Factor so here higher Precision really
implies increased resistance to
change the problem is that inertia alone
makes systems brittle errors they cannot
adapt so then we move to the second
component
elasticity elasticity describes the
system's ability to return to
characteristic or retractor States after
a
perturbation it corresponds to the
concept of homeostasis so the capacity
to adaptively
recover in active inference elasticity
is expressed in terms of an agent's
ability to minimize free energy and seek
stable
States it can be mapped onto the
relaxation back to attractor states
which is driven by minimizing free
energy as the system follows a
trajectory in doing so it restores the
system to a preferred state analogous to
returning to an attractor plant so for
example in nature biological systems
really exhibit elasticity through
homeostatic feedback mechanisms like
temperature regulation or blood glucose
balance these systems have the ability
to change but they ultimately return to
where uh they were without necessarily
learning and this may yield the same
errors and
ultimately can crap Under Pressure much
like a rubber band pulled too
hard so let's move on to the third
component
plasticity it refers to the expansion of
an agent's repertoire of adaptive States
it allows systems to adapt not only by
returning to previous States but also by
exploring new States enhancing
robustness
so in active inference plasticity is
related to functional redundancy and
structural
degeneracy having multiple Pathways to
achieve the same
outcome structural degeneracy means that
you have different components perform
overlapping roles allowing the system to
adapt to novel challenges but we will
dig into this a little
later so here plasticity is captured
through posterior beliefs that can
change flexibly based on new sensory
input or structure them if you actually
add a new
state we can use the variational density
such that the agent can represent a
diverse range of potential States
maintaining a dynamic model of its
environment think for example of neural
plasticity where different neural
circuits can adapt to perform similar
function after damage
to understand how plasticity comes into
play we really have to hone in on
certain key concept underlying it so
complexity refers to the uncertainty or
diversity of System
Dynamics in active
inference complexity is associated with
the range of possible States an agent
must consider
complexity is linked to entropy of the
system State
distribution higher entropy reflects
greater uncertainty and the number of
potential States the agent must account
for variational free energy is a way of
balancing two important things how
complex our beliefs are and how
accurately they match what we
observe and so we can U balance this in
a formula that goes f equals the
difference between the complexity of
updating our beliefs and how accurately
these beliefs predict what we
observe so this formula the first part
um DK measures the complexity or the
cost of updating our beliefs to align
with
reality the second part written as EQ
represents how well our current beliefs
can predict the observations we
make so we said we were going to turn to
degeneracy and redundancy and I'm
obviously here leveraging work um by no
uh and Carl
friston for degeneracy what we're
considering is that the presence of
different components are capable of
fulfilling similar roles within a system
in her paper they talked about for
example left hand right hand and
redundancy means that you have similar
components performing the same function
which enhances robustness against
failure the redundancy here involves
overlapping functions in state
transition matrices B which indicates
similar transitions across different
states and
degeneracy can be Quantified by the
entropy of the distribution which
represents the number of alternative
configurations that lead to similar
outcomes and so managing complexity
through diverse beliefs really means
that the agents can adapt to changing
conditions degeneracy means the agent
can switch strategy when one pathway
becomes unavailable which promotes
adaptation and redundancy ensures the
continuity function when certain
components fail which adds resilience to
the
system so degeneracy here helps reduce
the complexity cost by Distributing
probabilities across multiple States
thus maintaining low free energy and
supporting robustness in diverse
conditions but while resilience is
really critical for maintaining
stability it doesn't fully capture the
dynamic interaction between systems and
their
environments resilience focuses on an
agent's ability to withstand or recover
from
perturbations but it lacks insight into
the broader System
Dynamics without considering systemic
interdependencies focusing solely on
resilience can lead to shortterm adapt
ation without promoting long-term
stability this is work that Mark Miller
and inisha Palo have uh written a lot
about so for sustainability we really
need that um systems not only adapt but
also ensure the long-term viability of
their environment and resource
base we can through active inference
integrate resilience and sustainability
and and show the need for systemwide
coordination for harmonious interaction
as Carl likes to
say active inference really is just the
story of resilient and sustainable
systems so let's Define sustainability a
little
more sustainability is defined as the
enduring capacity to meet needs without
depleting crucial resources and here
resources is taken a little more
liberally we can expand Beyond material
resources and Encompass social
ecological and System
Dynamics sustainable systems are those
that persist over time and do so in a
manner that promotes stability and
health across all dimensions
environmental economic and
social we achieve this under active
inference by
enhancing
longterm adaptability and
interconnectedness across multiple
scales sustainability emphasizes the
creation of conditions that allow for
continued adaptation without exhausting
resources effectively ensuring that all
parts of the system work cohesively to
support resource renewal and
plasticity so sustainability can be
framed as optimizing the expected free
energy over deep temporal scales which
is work that Casper hesp uh has
pioneered balancing immediate needs with
long-term system viability
so the optimization of expected free
energy can be represented as um f of
expected uh SMA equals the risk plus the
ambiguity of X of f expected
s so risk quantifies the Divergence
between the predicted paths I.E the
future states of the system given an
action sequence and past
observations and and the preferred paths
which are ideally sustainable and align
with long-term
goals this encourages the system to
pursue states that meet its
sustainability preferences over time
ambiguity measures the expected
uncertainty in mapping states to
observations and it ensures that the
system continuously learns about its own
Dynamics and the
environment this helps the system reduce
UNC
and improve its predictive Dynamics um
over
time the components of expected free
energy balance the drive to fulfill
preferences with the need to minimize
uncertainty and so this balance supports
plastic responses that enable the system
to adapt to change but also actively
guide itself towards more sustainable
and self-organizing configurations over
extended time scales ensuring resilience
at both
individual and Collective
levels but sustainability isn't just
about survival or at least it's not a
simple story it must incorporate UD
dionic well-being focused on growth
fulfillment and development and honic
well-being which captures immediate
satisfaction so in active inference this
means that the system should balance
present experiences with long strm
strategies that enhance overall capacity
for adaptive growth so when we talk
about a dionic well-being we represent
growth and the system uh the system's
ability to find diverse beneficial
States and it aligns with long-term
sustainability by ensuring that in
survive and thrive through extended
adaptability and resource
renewal it represents the growth and
systems ability to achieve it's
long-term goals this this concept aligns
with active inference because it
emphasizes long-term
sustainability uh by optimizing internal
models that allow agents to find those
beneficial States and So within active
inference agents act to minimize
expected free energy which involves the
balance as we saw between risk
minimization which means that the
outcomes are aligned with the agent's
preferences and ambiguity minimization
which ensures that the learning
continuously happens so that's what
enables the agent to grow and
Thrive and so UD dionic well-being can
be conceptualized as the successful
maintenance of favorable States and the
expansion of the system's potential
allowing it to reach higher order goals
over extended time
Horizons and so this Behavior reflects
structure learning wherein agents adapt
to changes in the environment by
restructuring their inter internal
models which lead to growth in a diverse
set of beneficial States
now honic well-being involves immediate
momentto moment satisfaction which is
necessary to maintain ongoing motivation
and effective response to environmental
demands it focuses on immediate
satisfaction and so the agent's capacity
to respond adaptively to current needs
uh it can be seen in active inference as
the system's ability to reduce momentary
free energy and maximize instantaneous
rewards so we can see this at the lower
level say of hierarchical
models so you minimize prediction errors
in the present you seek sensory states
that satisfy immediate needs or
preferences like finding food to satisfy
hunger and this corresponds to reducing
free energy associated with specific
observations the internal reward or
momentary satisfaction that the agent
achieves after fulfilling immediate
needs corresponds to the agent reaching
a preferred State as predicted by its
inter
this is crucial for maintaining
motivation and ensuring effective
responses to environmental
demand here we also have to factor
interdependencies within the system
these interdependencies can be
represented through mutual uh
information equations which uh
ultimately um quantify the connections
between different components the
plasticity at different at individual
levels translate to the sustainability
of the entire system system aligning
short-term actions with uh long-term
goals so sustainability is an emergent
property that depends on the balance
between all elements in a system this
really involves presenting resource
depletion maintaining well-being and
promoting resilience through
self-organization and learning so it's a
continuous effort to increase resource
redundancy and a void overe exploitation
thereby ensuring sustainable practices
over time you can think of it as
avoiding a local
minimum the sustainability of a system
depends on harmonious interactions among
its different components which range
from Individual agents to the broader
Collective this means that the system
must align both internal and external
goals to ensure stability over extended
periods enhancing resilience and
sustainability
so uh for example uh the resilience
components of inertia elasticity and
plasticity will work synergistically to
support adaptive actions that contribute
to sustainable
outcomes the emergence stability is
promoted through decentralized
interactions where each component of the
system self-organizes and responds to
environmental feedback which reduces the
complexity and increases adaptive
capacity and allows the system to
maintain a dynamic but stable
equilibrium also sometimes referred to
as
omesis so we can think of attractor
states which emerge as agents minimize
their V variational free energy over
time and this process supports the
alignment of internal models with the
environmental demands ensuring that
agents remain adaptive while reinforcing
the renewal of resources and overall
system wellbeing
so these are all nice ideas and you know
we think they hold up mathematically but
we wanted to test them out and obviously
this is the beginning of the journey so
we built a small and very simple agent
based models to illustrate
sustainability under active inference at
the level of one single agent within one
environment this is extremely simple and
the following studies will cover more so
the model here simulates an agent
managing food consumption in different
environments to ensure long-term
resource
availability our objective was to show
that uh the agent's goal is to maximize
well-being while ensuring resource
sustainability over time and this
involves balancing immediate needs with
uh future availability of
resources so we started with a
validation case um in this case the
agent makes decisions uh based on
current food availability without
affecting future availability and so the
agent observes food and decides whether
to consume or not uh based on its
current state and prior
preferences so we have the generative
model uh we have hidden States
representing food availability and saity
and the preference uh C which encoded a
strong preference for saity while
maintaining food availability as as you
can see these two preferences are
technically
contradicted and so in a static
environment which was the first case the
agent decisions are really
straightforward they just maximize
short-term well-being without needing to
manage resource
Dynamics so as you can see uh in the
tiny little plots here uh the we can see
that the agent's Behavior specifically
uh whether the agent chooses to eat or
not over a series of time steps and so
uh the middle plot shows that the amount
of food over time which is represented
as food left and the last bottom plot
shows that uh the uh you represent the
agent's level of SA or how satisfied or
full the agent feels over time higher
values indicate higher levels of sa and
so uh the agent uh has a strong
preference for high sty uh since food is
continuously available the agent keeps
eating at the beginning which increases
its saity level and since the
environment is static the food remains
available indefinitely and so the agent
successfully increases its
H uh we then wanted to show whether or
not what we did was just an artifact of
the Simplicity of the model so we
screwed with its matrices and so
incorrect matrices cause the agent to
misjudge the effect of eating which
leads to an unstable sa level so we we
showed how errors in perception and
action models can significantly impact
the ability of an agent to achieve
stable and desirable States even in an
extremely simple uh setup
so then we tried something a little more
complicated which is a dynamic
environment where the strategies have to
change so uh the environment changes
based on the agent's actions so
resources deplete when consumed but
replenish over time when not used and so
the agent's challenge was that it had to
learn to balance consumption with
replenishments uh which effectively had
to demonstrate some degree of
sustainable Behavior
so the model includes the transition
Matrix that Maps the state of food
available based on the agent's actions
and expected free energy here
minimization uh guides the agent to
consider future State and ensure
resource
availability um so this was the case as
you can see it hasn't changed much the
only thing that has changed is the
Dynamics of the environment and the
ability for the agent to ultimately
learn those
Dynamics so the agent had to ad adaptive
strategies that balanced immediate
rewards with long-term stability uh and
this was showing us how active inference
can foster sustainable behaviors in
fluctuating
environments um so when we look at this
plot um we could see that the agent uh
has learning turned on or not and we
wanted to see whether an agent that
didn't learn did just as well as an
agent who learn just to see again
whether it was an artifact of the
Simplicity of our model and also the
agent can die if the resources are
depleted and it has high sa it is not
satiated over time it dies which you
know ethically might not have been the
best thing to do but
whatever so agents that have learning
quickly improve their survival Times by
refining their internal models and
strategies and so the rapid Improvement
really shows that learning enables them
to find efficient and sustainable ways
to interact with their environment
without learning there is no significant
increase uh in survival time uh as they
unable to really adapt their behavior
based on past experiences so they end up
uh in suboptimal decision Loops leading
to a lower average
survival so we can really show that
learning is crucial for agents's ability
to adapt which in turn allows for a
longer more sustainable uh presence in
the environment and ultimately uh you
know the also the environment's ability
to actually be sustainable in itself the
agent overcomes initial limitations
eventually converges to strategies that
maximize our survival which really shows
the power of dynamic adaptation in
uncertain
environments so we saw that the agent's
behavior in both static and dynamic
environments really shows how well-being
can be optimized while maintaining
resource availability and in the dynamic
environment the agent learns to moderate
consumption it is able to understand the
tradeoff between immediate satisfaction
and future resource
sustainability the agent has the ability
to create adaptive strategies that adapt
uh that align sorry with the principles
of resilience and
sustainability and so here our model
illustrates in a very very minimal way
how minimizing free energy can lead to
behaviors that promote long-term
viability rather than short-term
gains and so these simple models are
just laying the groundwork for modeling
more complex systems such as ecosystems
or Urban environments where
sustainability requires coordinated
interactions between multiple agents and
resources so to
recap we started by understanding
resilience with an active inference we
broke it down to inertia elasticity and
plasticity we then explored
sustainability building on resilience
and we incorporated well-being as a
component we demonstrated how agents can
balance immediate needs and future
viability achieving sustainability again
all through active
inflence and so it Maps systems that can
adapt sustain and Thrive by balancing
short-term adaptation with long-term
sustainability but we still need to show
how active inference can effectively be
scaled to real world applications
involving multiple interacting agents
and resources uh involving the ability
for the environment to fully deplete and
therefore how to actually manage such
possible um such possible patterns and
how agents might learn over different
areas um we have to transition from
theoretical models to more practical
implications that involve challenges in
data acquisition model complexity
computational
scalability um we also need to factor
Mutual interactions and the effects of
each subsystem on each other and the
larger system such that they promote
more resilience and plasticity so all of
this is extremely seminal we have to
move uh further and actually demonstrate
in much larger scale and more
complex simulations this these
ideas but it has critical potential
applications achieving all this we can
use active inference to model and
predict adaptive strategies for
mitigating climate impacts at different
scales or improve decision-making
processes in organization
uh enhancing resilience and
sustainability in economic and social
contexts so active inference can be
extended to other complex adaptive
system and we can support initiatives
aimed at fostering sustainability in
health care Agriculture and urban
planning which is work that again Mark
Miller and Ben White tenesi poo uh are
really pushing
forward so thank you for listening and I
hope you enjoyed